My name is Nanfu. In Chinese, "nan" means "man." And "fu" means "pillar." My family had hoped for a boy, who would grow up to be the pillar of the family. And when I turned out to be a girl, they named me Nanfu anyway. (Laughter) I was born in 1985, six years before China announced its one-child policy. Right after I was born, the local officials came and ordered my mom to be sterilized. My grandpa stood up to the officials, because he wanted a grandson to carry on the family name. Eventually, my parents were allowed to have a second child, but they had to wait for five years and pay a substantial fine. Growing up, my brother and I were surrounded by children from one-child families. I remember feeling a sense of shame because I had a younger brother. I felt like our family did something wrong for having two children. At the time, I didn't question where this sense of shame and guilt came from. A year and a half ago, I had my own first child. It was the best thing that ever happened in my life. Becoming a mother gave me a totally new perspective on my own childhood, and it brought back my memories of early life in China. For the past three decades, everyone in my family had to apply for a permission from the government to have a child. And I wondered what it was like for people who lived under the one-child policy. So I decided to make a documentary about it. One of the people I interviewed was the midwife who delivered all of the babies born in my village, including myself. She was 84 years old when I interviewed her. I asked her, "Do you remember how many babies you delivered throughout your career?" She didn't have a number for deliveries. She said she had performed 60,000 forced abortions and sterilizations. Sometimes, she said, a late-term fetus would survive an abortion, and she would kill the baby after delivering it. She remembered how her hands would tremble as she did the work. Her story shocked me. When I set out to make the film, I expected it would be a simple story of perpetrators and victims. People who carried out the policy and people who are living with the consequences. But that wasn't what I saw. As I was finishing my interview with the midwife, I noticed an area in her house that was decorated with elaborate homemade flags. And each flag has a picture of a baby on it. These were flags that were sent by families whom she helped treat their infertility problems. She explained that she had had enough of performing abortions and sterilizations -- that the only work she did now was to help families have babies. She said she was full of guilt for carrying out the one-child policy, and she hoped that by helping families have babies, she could counteract what she did in the past. It became clear to me she, too, was a victim of the policy. Every voice was telling her that what she did was right and necessary for China's survival. And she did what she thought was right for her country. I know how strong that message was. It was everywhere around myself when I grew up. It was printed on matches, playing cards, textbooks, posters. The propaganda praising the one-child policy was everywhere around us. [Anyone who refuses to sterilize will be arrested.] And so were the threats against disobeying it. The message seeped into our minds so much so that I grew up feeling embarrassed for having a younger brother. With each person I filmed, I saw how their minds and hearts can be influenced by the propaganda, and how their willingness to make sacrifices for the greater good can be twisted into something very dark and tragic. China is not the only place where this happens. There is no country on earth where propaganda isn't present. And in societies that are supposed to be more open and free than China, it can be even harder to recognize what propaganda looks like. It hides in plain sight as news reports, TV commercials, political campaigning and in our social media feeds. It works to change our minds without our knowledge. Every society is vulnerable to accepting propaganda as truth, and no society where propaganda replaces the truth can be truly free. Thank you. (Applause)
Me llamo Nanfu. En chino, "nan" significa "hombre". Y "fu" significa "pilar". Mi familia había deseado un niño, que al crecer se convirtiera en el pilar de la familia. Y al nacer yo, me llamaron Nanfu igual. (Risas) Nací en 1985, seis años antes de que China introdujera su política del hijo único. Justo después de que nací, los funcionarios le ordenaron a mi madre que se esterilizara. Mi abuelo enfrentó a los funcionarios, porque quería un nieto que perpetuara el apellido de la familia. Al final, se permitió a mis padres tener un segundo hijo, pero debieron esperar cinco años y pagar una multa elevada. Durante nuestra infancia, mi hermano y yo estábamos rodeados de niños de familias con un solo hijo. Recuerdo sentir vergüenza por tener un hermano menor. Sentí que nuestra familia había hecho algo malo al tener dos hijos. En ese momento, no me pregunté cuál era la raíz de esta vergüenza y esta culpa. Hace un año y medio, tuve mi primer hijo. Fue lo mejor que me ha pasado en la vida. Convertirme en madre me dio una nueva perspectiva de mi propia infancia, y revivió recuerdos de mi juventud en China. Durante las últimas tres décadas, todos en mi familia debieron solicitar permiso del gobierno para tener un hijo. Y me pregunté: ¿cómo era la vida para la gente sometida a la política del hijo único? Entonces decidí hacer un documental sobre esto. Una de las personas que entrevisté fue la partera que se encargó de todos los partos de mi aldea, incluso del parto en que nací yo. Tenía 84 años cuando la entrevisté. Le pregunté: "¿Recuerda cuántos partos asistió en toda su carrera?". No tenía un número exacto. Me dijo que había practicado 60 000 abortos forzados y esterilizaciones. A veces, me explicó, un feto sobrevivía al aborto, y ella mataba al bebé después del parto. Recordó cómo le temblaban las manos al realizar este trabajo. Su historia me impactó. Cuando empecé a hacer la película, esperaba que fuera una historia sencilla de responsables y víctimas, de gente que ejecutó la política y de la gente que sufre sus consecuencias. Pero no fue eso lo que encontré. Mientras acababa mi entrevista con la partera, noté un área de su casa que estaba decorada con elaboradas banderas caseras. Cada bandera tiene la foto de un bebé. Eran regalos de las familias cuyos problemas de infertilidad ella había ayudado a tratar. Me contó que estaba harta de practicar abortos y esterilizaciones, y que ahora su trabajo se centraba en ayudar a que las familias tuvieran hijos. Me contó que se sentía llena de culpa por haber ejecutado la política del hijo único, y esperaba que el ayudar a las familias a tener hijos pudiera compensar lo que hizo en el pasado. Quedó claro que ella era víctima de la política también. Todos le decían que su trabajo era esencial y necesario para que China sobreviviera. E hizo lo que consideró apropiado para su país. Sé lo fuerte que era ese mensaje. Al crecer, podía verlo en todas partes. Se imprimía en cajas de cerillas, en naipes, en libros, pósteres. La propaganda que elogiaba la política se encontraba en todas partes. [Todo aquel que se niegue a esterilizarse será detenido.] Había amenazas generalizadas también. El mensaje se filtró en nuestras mentes, tanto así que crecí sintiéndome avergonzada por tener un hermano menor. En cada persona que filmé, pude ver cómo su mente y corazón habían sido influenciados por la propaganda, y cómo su disposición a sacrificarse por un bien mayor había sido distorsionada en algo muy oscuro y trágico. China no es el único lugar donde ocurre esto. No existe ningún país del mundo que esté libre de propaganda. En las sociedades que supuestamente son más abiertas y libres que China, puede ser aún más difícil detectar la propaganda. Se esconde a simple vista en forma de reportajes, comerciales de televisión, campañas políticas y ahora en las redes sociales. Está diseñada para cambiar la opinión de la gente sin que lo noten. Toda sociedad es vulnerable a tomar la propaganda como verdad, y no es posible que una sociedad sea verdaderamente libre si la propaganda reemplaza la verdad. Gracias. (Aplausos)